RG 005:025, Office of the Governor: John Harper Trumbull (1925-1931)
Connecticut State Library
John Harper Trumbull records
1925-1931
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Governor (1925-1931: Trumbull)
29.5 cubic feet
Gov. John H. Trumbull's subject files.
RG005_025
T001242
Biographical Note
Born: March 4, 1873, Ashford, Connecticut.
College: None.
Political Party: Republican.
Offices: Lt. Governor of Connecticut, 1925; Governor of Connecticut, 1925-1931.
Died: May 21, 1961, Hartford, Connecticut.
Because Hiram Bingham resigned after one day in office, John Trumbull served the shortest term of any lieutenant governor in the state. Despite his famous Connecticut name, he was not related to any of the three previous Trumbulls who had served as governors. His parents were Irish immigrants who moved to Ashford in the early 1870's to operate a farm. Trumbull was born there in 1873, but the family later moved to Plainville where he developed an interest in the emerging industry of electricity. In 1898 he and a brother formed an electrical business in Plainville in partnership with another man. Known as the Trumbull Electric Company, it produced appliances and later became part of General Electric. Trumbull was its president from 1911 until he retired from the company in 1944. He was also active in other business firms. Trumbull had an interest in the militia and joined the First Connecticut Infantry in 1891. He achieved the rank of colonel in the State Guard. He also developed an interest in flying and piloted his own airplanes during speaking engagements. This earned him the title of. Flying Governor. Trumbull married Maud Usher in 1903 and they had two children.
With Bingham leaving office on January 8, 1925, Trumbull served that complete term as governor and was reelected two more times. He chose to retire in 1931. As a conservative Republican, he balanced the state's budget and sought to assist Connecticut's businesses. During his terms the state government began a building program and worked to improve Connecticut's roads. When the Great Depression came in 1929 Trumbull was unable to prevent the state's unemployment from growing nor to solve its financial problems. Trumbull did seek to become governor again in 1932, but lost to the incumbent, Wilbur Cross.
When Trumbull left office he continued overseeing his business interests. He was also an active sportsman. The Museum of Connecticut History owns a propeller from a plane he once crashed. It also owns a firearm that was presented to him by the Colt Company of Hartford. His factory building in Plainville still stands on Woodford Avenue.
Bibliography
Crofut, Florence S. Marcy. Guide to the History and the Historic Sites of Connecticut. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press, 1937 [CSL call number HistRef F 94 .C88 1937].
History of Hartford County, Connecticut, 1633-1928, Vol. 3, 1928, pp. 30-34.
Mitchell, Rowland W. Social Legislation in Connecticut, 1919-1939. Ph.D. Dissertation, Yale University, 1954.
Sobel, Robert and John Raimo. Biographical Directory of the Governors of the United States, 1789-1978. Westport, Conn.: Meckler Books, 1978. [CSL call number GIS Ref E 176 .B573].
Van Dusen, Albert E. Connecticut. New York: Random House, 1961. [CSL call number HistRef F 94 .V3].
Scope and Content
Gov. John H. Trumbull's records are subject files related to state agencies, commissions, legislative bills, and appointments among other topics.
Arrangement
Series 1. Subject Files.
Subseries 1. 1925-1927.
Subseries 2. 1927-1929.
Subseries 3. 1929-1931.
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Persons:
Trumbull, John Harper, 1873-1961
Subjects:
Trumbull, John Harper, 1873-1961 -- Archives; Connecticut. Office of the Governor -- Archives; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1919-1933 -- Sources; Governors -- Connecticut -- Archives
Document Types:
Correspondence; Records
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Subject Files, 1925-1931
  - 1925-1927
    - Acknowledgements (Box 308)
    - Adjutant General's Assistant, Applications for (Box 308)
    - Agriculture, Commissioner of (Box 308)
    - Agriculture, State Dept. of (Box 308)
    - Air Mail Service (Box 308)
    - American Legion, The (Box 308)
    - American School for the Deaf (Box 308)
    - Appointments - Recommendations for (Box 308)
    - Appointments - Requesting (Box 308)
    - Associations, Societies, Clubs, Conferences (Box 308)
    - Associations, 1926 (Box 309)
    - Attorney General's Opinions (Box 309)
    - Aviation (Box 309)
    - Bank Commissioner (Box 309)
    - Barbers Commission (Box 309)
    - Bills - Motion Picture Bill (Box 309)
    - Bill - Sunday Baseball (Box 309)
    - Bills & Gen [eral] Assembly (Miscellaneous) (Box 310)
    - Bingham, Hiram (Personal) (Box 310)
    - Blind, Board of Education of (Box 310)
    - Blind - Reports (Box 310)
    - Board of Control (Box 310)
    - Board of Control - Notice of Hearings (Box 310)
    - Board of Control - Notice of Hearings (Box 310)
    - Board of Pardons, 2 folders (Box 310)
    - Boundaries - N[ew]Y[ork] - Conn[ecticut], Mass[achusetts] - Conn[ecticut (Box 310)
    - Boy Scouts (Box 310)
    - Brainard, Lt. Governor (Personal) (Box 310)
    - Child Welfare, Bureau of (Box 311)
    - Coal, 1925 (Box 311)
    - Commissioners of Deeds (Box 311)
    - Compensation Commissioner (Box 311)
    - Complaints (Box 311)
    - Comptroller (Box 311)
    - Connecticut Agricultural College (Box 311)
    - Connecticut Agricultural College, Minutes of Meetings (Box 311)
    - Connecticut Agricultural College, Storrs, Study of - Report (Box 312)
    - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 312)
    - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 50th Anniversary of (Box 312)
    - Connecticut Chamber of Commerce (Box 312)
    - Connecticut College Endowment Fund - New London (Box 312)
    - Connecticut Prison Association (Box 312)
    - Connecticut River - Mass. Rivers Special Investigation by Caleb M. Saville (Box 312)
    - Connecticut School for Boys (Box 312)
    - Connecticut State Fair (Box 312)
    - Connecticut State Hospital (Box 312)
    - Connecticut State Hospital - Notice of Meetings (Box 312)
    - County Commissioner - New London County (Box 312)
    - County Commissioner - Tolland County (Box 312)
    - County Commissioner - Windham County (Box 312)
    - County Jails (Box 312)
    - County Jails - Examination of Insane (Box 312)
    - Credentials, 1926 (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Dairy and Food (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Fish and Game (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Health (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Prison (Box 313)
    - Credentials - State Parks (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Tax (Box 313)
    - Credentials - Uniform State Laws (Box 313)
    - Dairy and Food Commission (Box 313)
    - Dental Commissioners (Box 313)
    - Department of Public Welfare (Box 313)
    - Department of State, Washington [D. C.] (Box 313)
    - Domestic Animal Commission (Box 313)
    - Educational Commission (Box 313)
    - Education, State Board of (Box 313)
    - Education, State Board of - Appropriations Budget (Box 313)
    - Education, State Board of - Meetings (Box 313)
    - Elections, Special - Brookfield (Box 314)
    - Employment File, Applications (Box 314)
    - Extraditions, See Requisitions (Box 314)
    - Fish and Game, State Dep[artmen]t of (Box 314)
    - Geological and Natural History Survey Commission (Box 314)
    - Governors' Conference (National) (Box 314)
    - Hairdressers' Commission (Box 314)
    - Healing Arts Board - (See Medical Exam[ining] Board) (Box 314)
    - Henry Whitfield House Commission (Box 314)
    - Highway Commission, State (Box 314)
    - Homeopathic Board (Box 314)
    - Immigration (Box 314)
    - Insurance Commissioner (Box 314)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission (Box 315)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission - printed matter (Box 315)
    - Invitations (Box 315)
    - Judge of Enfield Town Court (Box 315)
    - Judge of Southington Court (Box 315)
    - Judge of Stamford Court (Box 315)
    - Lexington Sesqui-Centennial Celebration (Box 315)
    - Long Lane Farm (Box 315)
    - Mansfield State Training School and Hospital (Box 315)
    - Manufacturers Asso [ciation] of Conn [ecticut] (Box 315)
    - Medical Examining Board (Box 315)
    - Military, 1925 (Box 316)
    - Military - Troop "B" Armory - Petition (Box 316)
    - Miscellaneous, 1925 (Box 316)
    - Motor Vehicle Commissioner (Box 316)
    - Naturopathy Board (Box 317)
    - Navy and Marine Memorial (Box 317)
    - New England Council (Box 317)
    - New England Governors' Conference (Box 317)
    - New England Governors' Conference Reports - Special Comm [ission] Appointed (Box 317)
    - New Haven and Shore Line RR (Box 317)
    - Newington Home for Crippled Children (Box 317)
    - Newington Home for Crippled Children - Health Reports (Box 317)
    - Newington Home for Crippled Children - Minutes of meetings (Box 317)
    - Norwalk Harbor (Box 317)
    - Norwich State Hospital (Box 317)
    - Notaries, 1925 (Box 318)
    - Notaries, 1926 (Box 318)
    - Notice of Governor's Absence from the State (Box 318)
    - Park Policemen (Box 319)
    - Pharmacy Commission (Box 319)
    - Philadelphia Sesqui-Centennial Celebration (Box 319)
    - Pollution Commission (Box 319)
    - Pollution of Streams (Box 319)
    - Portrait of Governor - Applications [from artists] (Box 319)
    - President Coolidge (Box 319)
    - Press Matters (Box 319)
    - Proclamations and Statements (Box 319)
    - Prohibition (Box 320)
    - Public Utilities Commission (Box 320)
    - Railroad Matters (Box 320)
    - Railroad Policemen (Box 320)
    - Reports - Miscellaneous (Box 320)
    - Resignations (Box 320)
    - Rewards - Offer of (Box 320)
    - Requisitions (Box 321)
    - Rivers, Harbors and Bridges Commission (Box 321)
    - Save the Constitution Fund (Box 321)
    - Society of Executives (Box 321)
    - Soldiers - Fitch's Home for Soldiers (Box 321)
    - Soldiers Hospital Board [Also includes Minutes of Meetings], 1925-1926 (Box 321)
    - Soldiers - National Home for Disabled Volunteer Soldiers (Box 321)
    - Speaking Dates During Campaign (Box 322)
    - Special Investigating Committee Treasury Dep[artmen]t (Box 322)
    - State Agencies and Institutions (Box 322)
    - State's Attorneys (Box 322)
    - State Athletic Commission (Box 322)
    - State Board of Health (Box 322)
    - State Farm for Women (Box 322)
    - State Institutions, Commission (Box 322)
    - State Library (Box 322)
    - State Officers, 1925 January-August (Box 323)
    - State Officers, 1925 August (Box 323)
    - State Park and Forest Comm[ission] (Box 323)
    - State Police, Department of (Box 323)
    - State Prison (Box 323)
    - State Treasurer (Box 323)
    - State Water Commission (Box 323)
    - Statements (Box 323)
    - Tax Commissioner (Tax Matters) (Box 323)
    - Tuberculosis Commission, State (Box 324)
    - Uniform Court Charters (Box 324)
    - United States Senate (Box 324)
    - Veterans Bureau, United States (Box 324)
    - Visits of Governor to Washington (Box 324)
    - War Trophies (Box 324)
    - War Trophies - Applications (Box 324)
    - Yale Corporation (Box 324)
    - Y.M.C.A. (Box 324)
  - 1927-1929
    - Acknowledgments (Box 325)
    - Agriculture, State Dept. of (Box 325)
    - American School for the Deaf (Box 325)
    - Appointments - Park Policemen (Box 325)
    - Appointments - Requesting office (Box 325)
    - Appointments - Special Committees and Commissions (Box 325)
    - Appointments - State Officers (Box 325)
    - Associations, Conferences, Clubs (Box 325)
    - Attorney General's Opinions (Box 326)
    - Aviation (Colonial and Personal, 1927 (Box 326)
    - Aviation (Colonial and Personal), 1928 (Box 326)
    - Aviation (State), 1927-1928 (Box 327)
    - Bank Commissioner (Box 327)
    - Bills - Coal and Fuel Administrator (Box 327)
    - Bills - Copies of Invoices (Box 327)
    - Bills - Motor Vehicle Licenses 16 Yrs. (Box 327)
    - Bills - Property Offered for the Erection of a New Insane Hosp[ital] (Box 327)
    - Bills - Soldiers Hosp[ital] (Box 327)
    - Bills - Sunday Movies (Box 327)
    - Blind, Board of Education of (Box 327)
    - Board of Control (Box 327)
    - Board of Control - Meetings (Box 327)
    - Board of Pardons (Box 327)
    - Brainard, Edwin, Lieut[enant] Gov[ernor] - Notice of Gov[ernor's] Absense from the State (Box 328)
    - Brainard, J. Edwin Lieut[enant] Gov[ernor] - Personal (Box 328)
    - Campaign (Box 328)
    - Chicago Radio Address (Box 328)
    - Child Welfare, Bureau of (Box 328)
    - Coal (Box 328)
    - Commissioner of Deeds (Box 328)
    - Complaints (Box 328)
    - Comptroller (Box 328)
    - Connecticut Agricultural College (Box 328)
    - Connecticut Agricultural College - Minutes of Meetings (Box 328)
    - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 329)
    - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station - Notice of Meetings (Box 329)
    - Connecticut Chamber of Commerce (Box 329)
    - Connecticut Prison Association (Box 329)
    - Connecticut Reformatory (Box 329)
    - Connecticut School for Boys (Box 329)
    - Connecticut State Hospital (Box 329)
    - County Jails (Box 329)
    - County Jails - Exam[ination] of Insane Persons (Box 329)
    - Credentials (Box 329)
    - Credentials - Dairy and Food Commissioner (Box 329)
    - Credentials - National Convention (Box 329)
    - Credentials - State Prison (Box 329)
    - Deeds (Box 330)
    - Dental Commissioner (Box 330)
    - Department of Public Welfare (Box 330)
    - Department of State - Washington (Box 330)
    - Domestic Animals Commission (Box 330)
    - Education, State B[oar]d of (Box 330)
    - Education, State Board of - Meetings (Box 330)
    - Education, State Board of - Reports (Box 330)
    - Election, Special - Madison - Judge of Probate (Box 330)
    - Finance, State Board of (Box 330)
    - Fish and Game Department (Box 330)
    - Flood, 1927 (Box 330)
    - Four Day Steamship Service (Box 330)
    - General Assembly Matters (Box 330)
    - Geological & Natural Survey Commission (Box 330)
    - Governor's Chauffeur (Bills) (Box 330)
    - Governors' Conference - National, 1927 (Box 330)
    - Governors' Conference - National, 1928 (Box 330)
    - Griffenhagen & Associates (Box 330)
    - Hairdressers' Commission (Box 331)
    - Highway Commission, State (Box 331)
    - Immigration (Box 331)
    - Insurance Commissioner (Box 331)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission (Box 331)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission - printed materials (Box 331)
    - Invitations (Box 331)
    - Invitations, 1928 (Box 331)
    - Judge of Probate (Box 332)
    - Judicial Council (Box 332)
    - Kelly, [Edward L.] Executive Secretary (Personal) (Box 332)
    - Labor, Dep[artmen]t of Factory & (Box 332)
    - Legislative (Box 332)
    - Long Lane Farm (Box 332)
    - Mansfield Training School & Hospital (Box 332)
    - Manufacturer's Asso[ciation] of Conn (Box 332)
    - Military (Box 332)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 333)
    - Miscellaneous (Unimportant) (Box 334)
    - Motor Vehicle Commissioner (Box 334)
    - Naturopathy (Box 334)
    - Navy Day, 1927-1928 (Box 334)
    - New England Council (Box 334)
    - Newington Home for Crippled Children (Box 334)
    - North Carolina Box Suit (Box 334)
    - Norwich State Hospital (Box 334)
    - Notaries Public (Box 335)
    - Notary Fees - Deposit Slips (Box 336)
    - Post Office (Hartford) (Box 336)
    - President Coolidge (Box 336)
    - Press Matters (Box 336)
    - Proclamations and Statements (Box 336)
    - Prohibition (Box 336)
    - Public Notices (Box 336)
    - Public Utilities Commission (Box 336)
    - Railroad Matters (Box 336)
    - Railroad Policemen (Box 336)
    - Reports (Box 337)
    - Requisitions (Box 338)
    - Resignations (Box 338)
    - Rewards - Offer of (Box 338)
    - Rivers, Harbors & Bridges Commission (Box 338)
    - Society of Executives (Box 338)
    - Soldiers, Fitch's Home for & Soldiers Hospital (Box 338)
    - Soldiers Hospital Board (Box 338)
    - Soldiers Hospital Board - Minutes of Meetings (Box 338)
    - Soldiers, National Home for Disabled Volunteers (Box 338)
    - State Agencies and Institutions (Box 339)
    - State Athletic Commission (Box 339)
    - State Attorneys (Box 339)
    - State Board of Accountancy (Box 339)
    - State Board of Health (Box 339)
    - State Farm for Women (Box 339)
    - State Institutions, Commission (Box 339)
    - State Library (Box 339)
    - State Park and Forest Commission (Box 339)
    - State Police, Dept. of (Box 339)
    - State Prison (Box 340)
    - State Treasurer (Box 340)
    - State Water Commission (Box 340)
    - Tax Commissioner (Tax Matters) (Box 340)
    - Tuberculosis Commission, State (Box 340)
    - United States Senate - Wash[ington] D.C (Box 340)
    - Veterans Bureau (Box 341)
    - War Trophies (Box 341)
    - Washington (Box 341)
    - Waterways - Conn[ecticut] River & Mass[achusetts] Ware & Swift Rivers (Box 341)
    - Y.M.C.A. (Box 341)
    - Yale Corporation (Box 341)
  - 1929-1931
    - Accountancy, State Board of (Box 342)
    - Agriculture, State Dep[artmen]t of (Box 342)
    - American Legion (Box 342)
    - American School for the Deaf (Box 342)
    - Anniversary Celebrations (Box 342)
    - Appointments - Requesting Office (Box 342)
    - Appointments - Special Committees and Commissions (Box 342)
    - Appointments - State Offices, 1929 January (Box 342)
    - Associations, Conferences, Clubs (Box 343)
    - Athletic Commission, State (Box 343)
    - Attorney General's Opinions (Box 343)
    - Aviation (Box 343)
    - Aviation - Colonial & Personal (Box 344)
    - Aviation - State (Box 344)
    - Bank Commissioner - State (Box 344)
    - Barbers Commission (Box 344)
    - Bill - General Assembly Matters (Box 345)
    - Bills - Special Session August, 1929 (Box 345)
    - Blind, B[oar]d of Education of (Box 345)
    - Board of Finance and Control (Box 345)
    - Board of Finance and Control - Meetings (Box 345)
    - Board of Pardons, 3 folders (Box 346)
    - Child Welfare, Bureau of (Box 346)
    - Coal (Box 346)
    - Commissioner to Investigate New Portland - Middletown Bridge (Box 346)
    - Commissioner of Deeds (Box 347)
    - Compensation Commissioner (Box 347)
    - Complaints (Box 347)
    - Comptroller (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Agricultural College (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Agriculture College - Minutes of Meetings (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Agricultural Experiment Station - Notice of Meetings (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Chamber of Commerce (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] Prison Association - Conn. Reformatory (Box 347)
    - Conn[ecticut] School for Boys at Meriden, 2 folders (Box 348)
    - Conn[ecticut] State Hospital [Middletown] (Box 348)
    - Conn[ecticut] Tercentenary (Box 348)
    - County Jails (Box 349)
    - Court of Common Pleas (Box 349)
    - Credentials (Box 349)
    - Credentials - Dairy and Food Commissioner (Box 349)
    - Dental Commissioner (Box 349)
    - Department of Public Welfare (Box 349)
    - Department of State - Washington (Box 349)
    - Domestic Animals Commission (Box 349)
    - Education, State Board of (Box 349)
    - Education, State Board of - Meetings (Box 349)
    - Education, State Board of - Reports (Box 349)
    - Elections - Special (Box 349)
    - Examiners of Embalmers, State Board of (Box 350)
    - Extraditions [See Requisitions] (Box 350)
    - Fish and Game Department (Box 350)
    - Forests and Wildlife, State Commission on (Box 350)
    - Fort Griswold Tract Commission (Box 350)
    - G. A. R. [Grand Army of the Republic] (Box 350)
    - Geological and Natural History Survey Commission (Box 350)
    - Governors' Conference National (Box 350)
    - Governors' Conference 1930 (Salt Lake City, Utah) (Box 350)
    - Hairdressers' Commission (Box 350)
    - Harbor Master (Box 350)
    - Hartford Chamber of Commerce (Box 350)
    - Healing Arts Board (See Medical Examining Board (Box 351)
    - Health, State Board of (Box 351)
    - Highway Commission, State (Box 351)
    - Immigration (Box 351)
    - Insurance Commissioner (Box 351)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission (Box 351)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission - Printed Matter (Box 351)
    - Invitations (Box 351)
    - Invitations, 5 folders (Box 352)
    - Invitations (Box 353)
    - Judge of Probate (Box 353)
    - Judicial Council (Box 353)
    - Kelly, Executive Secretary (Personal) (Box 353)
    - Labor, Dep[artmen]t of Factory & (Box 353)
    - Legislative (Box 353)
    - Long Lane Farm (Box 353)
    - Mansfield State Training School (Box 353)
    - Manufacturers' Association of Connecticut (Box 353)
    - Medical Examining Board (Box 353)
    - Metropolitan District Commission (Box 353)
    - Military (Box 354)
    - Military - Adjutant General's Orders (Box 354)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 355)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 356)
    - Motor Vehicle Commissioner (Box 356)
    - National Air Races - Chicago (Box 356)
    - National Safety Conference (Box 356)
    - New England Council (Box 356)
    - New York & New England Motorways Corporation (Box 356)
    - Newington Home for Crippled Children (Box 357)
    - Norwich State Hospital (Box 357)
    - Notaries Public (Box 357)
    - Notary Fees - Deposit Slips (Box 357)
    - Notices of Governor's Absence from the State (Box 357)
    - Nurses, State Board of - Examination and Registration (Box 357)
    - Park and Forest Commission (Box 357)
    - Pensions Commission (Box 357)
    - Political Campaign, 1930 (Box 357)
    - Post Office (Hartford) (Box 357)
    - Press Matters (Box 357)
    - Proclamations & Statements (Box 358)
    - Prohibition (Box 358)
    - Public Utilities Commission (Box 358)
    - Railroad Matters (Box 358)
    - Railroad Policemen (Box 358)
    - Reports - Miscellaneous (Box 358)
    - Reports - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 359)
    - Requisitions (Box 360)
    - Resignations (Box 360)
    - Rewards - Offer for (Box 360)
    - Rivers, Harbors & Bridges Commission (Box 360)
    - Rogers, Ernest E., Lieut. Gov. - Personal (Box 360)
    - "Save - A - Life" Campaign (Box 360)
    - Society of Executives (Box 360)
    - Soldiers - Aid from National Home (Box 360)
    - Soldiers - Fitch's Home for Soldiers (Box 360)
    - State Agencies & Institutions (Box 360)
    - State Attorneys (Box 360)
    - State Farm for Women (Box 360)
    - State Library (Box 361)
    - State Office Building (Box 361)
    - State Police (Box 361)
    - State Prison (Box 361)
    - State Treasurer (Box 362)
    - State Water Commission (Box 362)
    - Tax Commission (Tax Matters) (Box 362)
    - Taxes - National Bank Tax (Box 362)
    - Teachers' Retirement Board (Box 362)
    - Tuberculosis Commission, State (Box 362)
    - United States Senate - Wash[ington], D.C. (Box 362)
    - Veterans' Bureau (Box 363)
    - Washington (Box 363)
    - Waterways (Box 363)
    - Y.M.C.A (Box 363)
    - Yale Corporation (Box 363)